<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>Change Log</title>
        <author email="sindre@activeobjects.no">Sindre Mehus</author>
    </properties>

    <body>

        <script src="http://www.google-analytics.com/urchin.js" type="text/javascript"></script>
        <script type="text/javascript">
            _uacct = 'UA-110410-1';
            urchinTracker();
        </script>

        <section name="Change Log">
            <subsection name="Subsonic 3.5.beta2 - Sep 15, 2008">
                <ul>
                    <li>New: Fancy cover art zoom.</li>
                    <li>New: Transcoding pack is now included in Windows installer.</li>
                    <li>New: Updated German translation (thanks to Jörg Frommann) and Norwegian translation (thanks to jigsaw).</li>
                    <li>New: Added Ripserver theme.</li>
                    <li>Bugfix: Streaming to mobile phones now works better.</li>
                    <li>Bugfix: Made tray icon work on Vista (requires Java 6 or later).</li>
                    <li>Bugfix: Disable random playlist functionality if user is not authorized to play music.</li>
                    <li>Tech: Build number is now identical to Subversion revision.</li>
                </ul>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Subsonic 3.5.beta1 - Jul 10, 2008">
                <ul>
                    <li>New: Implemented music player for Java-enabled mobile phones. See <a href="http://www.activeobjects.no/subsonic/forum/viewtopic.php?t=1203">this forum topic</a>.</li>
                    <li>New: Support for personal images (avatars).</li>
                    <li>New: Support "read-only" view. See <a href="http://www.activeobjects.no/subsonic/forum/viewtopic.php?p=2435">this forum topic</a>.</li>
                    <li>New: Simplified user interface in settings pages. Now only one "Save" button.</li>
                    <li>New: Improved usability of coverart search page. Now also searches discogs.com.</li>
                    <li>New: Merge artists with same name, but located in different music folders.</li>
                    <li>New: Added option "Let others see what I am playing"</li>
                    <li>New: Added option "Always use web player". See <a href="http://www.activeobjects.no/subsonic/forum/viewtopic.php?t=1077">this forum topic</a>.</li>
                    <li>New: Nicer controls in modern browsers (Opera 9.5, Firefox 3, IE 7).</li>
                    <li>Bugfix: Lots of extra players are no longer created.</li>
                    <li>Bugfix: Fix minor bug with letter appearing if only file (not directory) exists. See <a href="http://www.activeobjects.no/subsonic/forum/viewtopic.php?t=1023">this forum topic</a>.</li>
                    <li>Bugfix: Make standalone version work on Linux without X11 server.</li>
                    <li>Bugfix: Make lyrics work again. See <a href="http://www.activeobjects.no/subsonic/forum/viewtopic.php?p=2588">this forum topic</a>.</li>
                    <li>Bugfix: Proper sorting of "The" artists. See <a href="http://www.activeobjects.no/subsonic/forum/viewtopic.php?t=1144">this forum topic</a>.</li>
                    <li>Bugfix: Make source release build.</li>
                </ul>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Subsonic 3.4 - Apr 27, 2008">
                <ul>
                    <li>New: Added optional setting for LDAP bind DN and password.</li>
                    <li>New: Added quick links to Google, Wikipedia, allmusic and Last.fm.</li>
                    <li>New: Added standalone installation option.</li>
                    <li>Bugfix: Fixed layout problems in Podcast page.</li>
                    <li>Bugfix: Clean up partially downloaded Podcast episodes at start-up.</li>
                    <li>Bugfix: Old Podcast episodes were in some cases not deleted.</li>
                </ul>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Subsonic 3.4.beta1 - Mar 28, 2008">
                <ul>
                    <li>New: Added support for user authentication in LDAP, including Microsoft Active Directory.</li>
                    <li>New: Implemented "Party mode" with a simpler user interface.</li>
                    <li>New: Added option to specify music folder in "Random playlist".</li>
                    <li>New: Added option "Play more random songs when end of playlist is reached" in "Random playlist".</li>
                    <li>New: Implemented download option in WAP interface.</li>
                    <li>New: Implemented random playlist option in WAP interface.</li>
                    <li>New: Make index always visible (doesn't work in IE).</li>
                    <li>New: Added play/add/download buttons for songs in left frame.</li>
                    <li>New: Suggest track number in tag editor.</li>
                    <li>Bugfix: Fixed faulty layout in main frame.</li>
                    <li>Bugfix: Fixed caching bug of left frame (when changing theme etc).</li>
                    <li>Bugfix: "Highest rated" now also shows albums that have never been played.</li>
                    <li>Bugfix: Player selection in WAP interface now works.</li>
                    <li>Bugfix: Support quotes in search field and shortcut field.</li>
                    <li>Bugfix: Don't display track number zero.</li>
                    <li>Tech: Faster start-up on Windows. Extract war file to SUBSONIC_HOME/jetty instead of temp directory.</li>
                    <li>Tech: Made it possible to run the Jetty version on Linux and other platforms.</li>
                    <li>Tech: Allow up to one week of idle time in Jetty.</li>
                </ul>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Subsonic 3.3 - Dec 23, 2007">
                <ul>
                    <li>New: Added "HD-720" and "Barents Sea" themes.</li>
                    <li>New: Improved layout of left and main frame.</li>
                    <li>New: Sort genres in "Edit tags".</li>
                    <li>Bugfix: Make transcoding work when combined with client-side playlist.</li>
                    <li>Bugfix: Case-insensitive sorting of artists.</li>
                    <li>Bugfix: Made genre parsing more robust.</li>
                    <li>Tech: Upgraded to Acegi 1.0.5</li>
                    <li>Tech: Upgraded to Spring 2.5</li>
                    <li>Tech: Make it compile with Java 5.</li>
                </ul>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Subsonic 3.3.beta1 - Nov 23, 2007">
                <ul>
                    <li>New: Implemented client-side playlists, including random skipping within songs
                        (see <em>Settings &gt; Players &gt; Playlist is managed by player</em>).</li>
                    <li>New: Support resumable downloads.</li>
                    <li>New: Rewrite stream URL if Subsonic is behind a proxy.</li>
                    <li>New: Added two new themes designed for large HD screens.</li>
                    <li>New: Added Russian translation by Iaroslav Andrusiak.</li>
                    <li>New: Made it possible to collapse/expand Podcast episodes. Improved layout and usability.</li>
                    <li>New: Added "Play on phone" option to wap interface.</li>
                    <li>New: Auto-focus on username field in login page.</li>
                    <li>New: Created new settings categories "Advanced" and "Personal".</li>
                    <li>New: Moved index from top to left frame.</li>
                    <li>Bugfix: Support Podcast folder that is located outside music folder.</li>
                    <li>Bugfix: Handle track number on the form "3/12"</li>
                    <li>Bugfix: Fixed concurrency bug when rendering wiki markup.</li>
                </ul>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Subsonic 3.2 - Oct 09, 2007">
                <ul>
                    <li>New: Added support for editing genre in ID3 tags.</li>
                    <li>New: Show miniature album images in "Now playing" sidebar.</li>
                    <li>Bugfix: Handle podcasts with colons in the name.</li>
                    <li>Bugfix: Handle podcasts without enclosures.</li>
                    <li>Bugfix: Handle song, album and artist names with special characters (&lt;, &gt; etc)</li>
                </ul>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Subsonic 3.2.beta1 - Sep 19, 2007">
                <ul>
                    <li>New: Download Podcasts with the new integrated Podcast receiver.</li>
                    <li>New: One-click installation with the new Windows installer.</li>
                    <li>New: Fetch lyrics automatically from www.metrolyrics.com.</li>
                    <li>New: See what others are playing in the new "Now playing" sidebar.</li>
                    <li>New: Play music directly in the browser with the new integrated Flash-based player.</li>
                    <li>New: New tag engine (entagged.sourceforge.net) supports tags in a lot of formats (mp3, ogg, flac, wav, wma, etc).</li>
                    <li>New: Added confirmation dialog when deleting playlists.</li>
                    <li>New: Remember selected music folder (in left frame) across sessions.</li>
                    <li>Bugfix: Fixed bug with rendering multiple status charts concurrently.</li>
                    <li>Tech: Added db admin tool.</li>
                </ul>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Subsonic 3.1 - Jul 30, 2007">
                <p>(No changes since 3.1.beta2)</p>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Subsonic 3.1.beta2 - Jul 23, 2007">
                <ul>
                    <li>New: Optimized scanning of music folders. Dramatic improvement for network disks.</li>
                    <li>Bugfix: Fixed minor concurrency bug in search index creation.</li>
                    <li>Bugfix: Make cache work if clocks on remote disks are out of sync.</li>
                    <li>Bugfix: Ensure that cover art images are ordered alphabetically.</li>
                    <li>Bugfix: Remove nag message for licensed users.</li>
                </ul>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Subsonic 3.1.beta1 - Jun 30, 2007">
                <ul>
                    <li>New: Added checkboxes to songs in playlist, with option to perform operations on all selected songs.</li>
                    <li>New: Now possible to specify genre and decade when generating random playlist.</li>
                    <li>New: Added menu option to sort playlist by track, album or artist.</li>
                    <li>New: Audioscrobbling is now more fault-tolerant. Will retry if Last.fm is down.</li>
                    <li>New: Replaced Google ads with a donation request message. Donors will not see the message.</li>
                    <li>New: Added new attribute "default" to transcodings. When "default" is true, the transcoding is automatically activated
                        for new players.</li>
                    <li>New: Implemented support for browser caching of left frame (with artist list).</li>
                    <li>New: Made downsampling command configurable.</li>
                    <li>New: Switch to "Now playing" after 3 minutes of inactivity.</li>
                    <li>New: Album page now has link to artist.</li>
                    <li>Bugfix: Logically delete/undelete metadata for albums that disappear/reappear on disk.</li>
                    <li>Bugfix: Fixed ugly checkboxes in IE.</li>
                </ul>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Subsonic 3.0 - Mar 22, 2007">
                <p>(Changes since 3.0.beta2)</p>
                <ul>
                    <li>New: Added Google ads.</li>
                    <li>Tech: Upgraded <a href="http://code.google.com/p/jvorbiscomment/">jvorbiscomment</a> library.</li>
                    <li>Bugfix: Artists from different music folders are now properly sorted.</li>
                </ul>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Subsonic 3.0.beta2 - Feb 24, 2007">
                <ul>
                    <li>New: Added per-user bitrate limit.</li>
                    <li>New: Show error message in browser if Subsonic home can't be created.</li>
                    <li>Bugfix: Fixed remaining bugs (hopefully) related to folders with non-latin characters.</li>
                    <li>Bugfix: Zooming of ID3 cover art now works.</li>
                    <li>Bugfix: last.fm password must no longer be entered every time.</li>
                </ul>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Subsonic 3.0.beta1 - Feb 04, 2007">
                <ul>
                    <li>New: Audioscrobbling support. Automatically register what you're playing on last.fm.</li>
                    <li>New: Support display and editing of OGG Vorbis tags.</li>
                    <li>New: Display cover art embedded in ID3 tags.</li>
                    <li>New: Dutch translation by Ronald Knot.</li>
                    <li>New: Links to previous/next album by same artist.</li>
                    <li>New: Change tab order in login screen.</li>
                    <li>Bugfix: Support directory names with non-latin characters.</li>
                    <li>Bugfix: Fixed ampersand bug in wap interface.</li>
                    <li>Bugfix: Display hours for very long tracks.</li>
                    <li>Tech: Upgraded Spring and Acegi to latest versions.</li>
                </ul>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Subsonic 2.9 - Nov 13, 2006">
                <p>(Changes since 2.9.beta1)</p>
                <ul>
                    <li>New: Added German translation by Harald Weiss.</li>
                    <li>New: Show server version and memory usage in help page.</li>
                    <li>Bugfix: Don't hang if unable to resolve latest version number.</li>
                    <li>Bugfix: Avoid duplicates in random album page.</li>
                    <li>Bugfix: More robust ID3 parsing.</li>
                    <li>Bugfix: More robust thumbnail scaling.</li>
                    <li>Bugfix: Fixed bug which in some cases made it impossible to restart streams.</li>
                    <li>Bugfix: Improve track number removal from title.</li>
                </ul>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Subsonic 2.9.beta1 - Oct 16, 2006">
                <p>Development efforts in 2.9 have been focused on performance and quality, but there are some new
                    features as well.
                </p>
                <ul>
                    <li>Bugfix: Avoid excessive disk and memory usage when (re)scanning the music library (bug
                        introduced in 2.8).</li>
                    <li>Bugfix: Avoid flickering PNG images in IE.</li>
                    <li>New: Improved thumbnail quality using step-wise bilinear resampling.</li>
                    <li>New: Thumbnails are now cached in SUBSONIC_HOME/thumbs. Expect significant speed-ups (after a
                        while), in particular for huge images.</li>
                    <li>New: Improved search speed by a factor of two.</li>
                    <li>New: Miscellaneous other caching mechanisms for faster response times.</li>
                    <li>New: Support Wiki markup in album comments.</li>
                    <li>New: Added "Download" menu option to main album view.</li>
                    <li>New: Ratings are now per-user. Average rating is also displayed.</li>
                    <li>New: Now possible to delete rating (for current user).</li>
                    <li>New: Added Spanish translation by Jorge Bueno Magdalena. Gracias, Jorge!</li>
                    <li>New: New Subsonic logo.</li>
                    <li>New: Keep bitrate statistics even if player reconnects.</li>
                    <li>New: Support editing of track numbers in ID3 tags.</li>
                    <li>New: Show full file name as tool tip in ID3 tag editor.</li>
                    <li>New: Search results are now better sorted.</li>
                </ul>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Subsonic 2.8 - Sep 07, 2006">
                <p>(Changes since 2.8.beta1)</p>
                <ul>
                    <li>New: Added option for transcoders to obey the player max bitrate setting.</li>
                    <li>New: Sort songs by track number.</li>
                    <li>New: Added transcoding support for Shorten and WavPack.</li>
                    <li>New: Improved caching of cover art images in browser.</li>
                    <li>New: Scroller color in Sandstorm theme.</li>
                    <li>New: Updated Norwegian translation.</li>
                    <li>New: Added Simplified Chinese translation by Neil Gao (currently incomplete).</li>
                    <li>Bugfix: Fixed performance problem with "Home" page.</li>
                    <li>Bugfix: Fixed broken wap interface.</li>
                    <li>Bugfix: Fixed playlist autoscroll.</li>
                    <li>Bugfix: Proper rendering of directories with both files and sub-directories.</li>
                </ul>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Subsonic 2.8.beta1 - Aug 13, 2006">
                <ul>
                    <li>New: Transcoding plugin framework.</li>
                    <li>New: VBR (variable bitrate) detection and resampling.</li>
                    <li>New: Added form-based login with remember-me.</li>
                    <li>New: Added logout option.</li>
                    <li>New: Support per-user language and theme.</li>
                    <li>New: Show track number, genre, format, duration and file size.</li>
                    <li>New: Configurable level of song details.</li>
                    <li>New: Various artists detection.</li>
                    <li>New: Added option to stream over plain HTTP when using SSL.</li>
                    <li>New: Mouseover tooltip for truncated text and cover art images.</li>
                    <li>New: Optional notification of new final and beta releases.</li>
                    <li>New: Nicer error page.</li>
                    <li>New: Added "Back in black" and "Sandstorm" themes.</li>
                    <li>New: Exclude files and folders listed in "subsonic_exclude.txt"</li>
                    <li>Tech: New security implementation based on Acegi (http://acegisecurity.org/)</li>
                    <li>Tech: Springified WAP pages and servlets.</li>
                    <li>Tech: Springified DWR.</li>
                    <li>Tech: Springified DAO's and data source.</li>
                </ul>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Subsonic 2.7 - Jun 12, 2006">
                <ul>
                    <li>Tech: Subsonic was completely rewritten to use the Spring MVC framework.</li>
                    <li>New: Theme support. Now ships with two themes, "Subsonic Default" and "2 minutes to midnight".
                        Theme authors are encouraged to contribute.</li>
                    <li>New: Ajax-based ID3 tag editor.</li>
                    <li>New: Cover art 3D effect and popup. (3D effect not available in Internet Explorer).</li>
                    <li>New: Added options to limit bandwidth for downloads and uploads.</li>
                    <li>New: Added progress bar to upload page.</li>
                    <li>New: Show upload (as well as download and streaming) charts in status page.</li>
                    <li>New: Added option to configure shortcuts to certain folders.</li>
                    <li>New: Rating where you can see how much each user has uploaded/downloaded/streamed.</li>
                    <li>New: Nicer layout and graphics.</li>
                    <li>New: Added option to download playlists, both current and previously saved ones.</li>
                    <li>New: Now logs to c:/subsonic/subsonic.log (Windows) or /var/subsonic/subsonic.log (other platforms).</li>
                    <li>New: Support symbolic links on Unix.</li>
                    <li>New: Support XSPF playlist format.</li>
                    <li>New: Create backup of old image file when changing cover art.</li>
                    <li>Bugfix: Avoid wrapped lines if browser window is small.</li>
                    <li>Bugfix: Use proper Y-range in bandwidth charts.</li>
                    <li>Bugfix: Integer overflow in search index creation interval.</li>
                    <li>Bugfix: Some Amazon search didn't show any results.</li>
                    <li>Bugfix: Now possible to change cover art even if original file is write protected (Windows only).</li>
                </ul>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Subsonic 2.6 - Mar 10, 2006">
                <ul>
                    <li>New: Nicer layout, colors and icons. Customizable welcome message. Option to limit number of
                        cover art images to display.</li>
                    <li>New: You can now specify multiple media folders in the configuration.
                        This is useful, for example, if you have your music on multiple disks, or if you have one
                        directory with music, and another with movies. The index (on the left-hand side) can either show all
                        media folders (merged alphabetically), or you can select from a combo box which folder to display.</li>
                    <li>New: Assign ratings (one to five stars) and comments to individual albums.</li>
                    <li>New: There is a new welcome page, displaying lists of random albums, newest albums, highest
                        rated albums, most often played albums and most recently played albums.</li>
                    <li>New: You can configure a set of links to Internet TV and radio stations. These links become
                        available in the index on the left-hand side. Click on a link, and your player connects to the station.</li>
                    <li>New: Saved playlists are now available as Podcasts (available from the "More" page).</li>
                    <li>New: Improved player management. Support multiple players with the same IP address, and players
                        with dynamic IP addresses. Display player type (e.g., WinAmp) and last-seen date.</li>
                    <li>New: Macedonian translation by Stefan Ivanovski.</li>
                    <li>New: Implemented support for non-Latin character encodings (for instance Japanese or Cyrillic).</li>
                    <li>New: Added option to load a previously saved playlist in the WAP interface.</li>
                    <li>New: "Album Info" now integrates with Google Music.</li>
                    <li>New: Avoid unnecessary reloading of the playlist window.</li>
                    <li>Bugfix: Fallback to file name if ID3 tags are present but empty.</li>
                    <li>Bugfix: LAME now works on Linux.</li>
                    <li>Bugfix: Solved problem with playlist autoscroll on rearrange.</li>
                    <li>Bugfix: Clicking index in top frame sometimes caused reloading of left frame.</li>
                </ul>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Subsonic 2.5 - Nov 25, 2005">
                <ul>
                    <li>New: Implemented user management. Users are easily created, deleted and assigned different privileges.</li>
                    <li>New: Faster song switching. Players react immediately to playlist changes.</li>
                    <li>New: Now possible to refine search for cover art and album info.</li>
                    <li>New: Better support for OGG, AAC and other formats. Added proper suffix to stream URL as a hint
                        to the player.</li>
                    <li>New: Display media library statistics.</li>
                    <li>New: New location for preferences, search index and database (c:\subsonic or /var/subsonic).</li>
                    <li>Bugfix: Improved parsing of MP3 tags. Avoid funny characters in artist, album and song title.</li>
                </ul>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Subsonic 2.4 - Oct 10, 2005">
                <ul>
                    <li>New: Download cover art and album info from Amazon web service.</li>
                    <li>New: Show selection of random albums on welcome page.</li>
                    <li>New: Display notice if LAME is not installed.</li>
                    <li>Bugfix: Allow max one stream per player.</li>
                    <li>Bugfix: Use user-wide (not system-wide) preferences on non-Windows platforms.</li>
                </ul>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Subsonic 2.3 - May 28, 2005">
                <ul>
                    <li>Full internationalization support.</li>
                    <li>Automatic update of search index at specified intervals.</li>
                    <li>Search is now more like Google.</li>
                    <li>Updating search index is now a lot faster (30 seconds for 18000 songs).</li>
                    <li>Unique playlist "undo" function.</li>
                    <li>"Now Playing" automatically refreshes when a new album is played.</li>
                    <li>Ongoing downloads are now displayed in the status page, with charts showing download speed.</li>
                    <li>Some improvements in zip functionality.</li>
                    <li>Significantly improved accuracy in charts.</li>
                    <li>Better support for non-ASCII characters in SHOUTcast.</li>
                    <li>No longer necessary to enter username and password in player.</li>
                    <li>Support for "ignored articles".</li>
                    <li>Show log in help page.</li>
                </ul>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Subsonic 2.2 - March 17, 2005">
                <ul>
                    <li>Implemented SHOUTcast support.</li>
                    <li>Added "Album info" which links to reviews etc at allmusic.com.</li>
                    <li>Support for uploading files from the browser to the Subsonic server. Zip-files are automatically unpacked.</li>
                    <li>Improved usability in search interface.</li>
                    <li>Option to specify http://yourhostname/stream/file.ogg etc.</li>
                    <li>Bugfix: Detect zero-terminated strings in ID3 tags.</li>
                    <li>Bugfix: Use ID3v2 tags instead of ID3v1, if both are present.</li>
                </ul>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Subsonic 2.1 - March 8, 2005">
                <ul>
                    <li>Added more search options.</li>
                    <li>Added support for downloading an entire directory structure as a zip file.</li>
                    <li>Subsonic now parses song titles, artists and albums from ID3 tags.</li>
                    <li>Settings for cover art size and max bitrate can now be set for individual players.</li>
                    <li>Search index is now generated in the background.</li>
                    <li>Keep position in playlist frame (e.g., always show the currently playing track).</li>
                    <li>Some minor bug fixes.</li>
                </ul>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Subsonic 2.0 - February 27, 2005">
                <ul>
                    <li>Added WAP interface for controlling Subsonic from a mobile phone or PDA.</li>
                    <li>Added option to generate a random playlist.</li>
                    <li>Added option to download and save individual songs.</li>
                    <li>Subsonic now alerts users if a new version is available.</li>
                    <li>Improved documentation and usability.</li>
                    <li>ANT support.</li>
                </ul>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Subsonic 1.0 - February 10, 2005">
                <ul>
                    <li>Added chart for displaying bitrates last few minutes.</li>
                    <li>Implemented transcoding to lower bitrates.</li>
                    <li>Added online help.</li>
                    <li>Support PLS and M3U playlists.</li>
                </ul>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Subsonic 0.1 - December 14, 2004">
                <ul>
                    <li>Initial release.</li>
                </ul>
            </subsection>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>

