<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>Change Log</title>
        <author email="sindre_mehus@users.sourceforge.net">Sindre Mehus</author>
    </properties>
    

    <body>

        <script src="http://www.google-analytics.com/urchin.js" type="text/javascript"></script>
        <script type="text/javascript">
            _uacct = 'UA-110410-1';
            urchinTracker();
        </script>

        <section name="Change Log">

            <subsection name="Subsonic 2.7 - Jun 12, 2006">
                <ul>
                    <li>Tech: Subsonic was completely rewritten to use the Spring MVC framework.</li>
                    <li>New: Theme support. Now ships with two themes, "Subsonic Default" and "2 minutes to midnight".
                        Theme authors are encouraged to contribute.</li>
                    <li>New: Ajax-based ID3 tag editor.</li>
                    <li>New: Cover art 3D effect and popup. (3D effect not available in Internet Explorer).</li>
                    <li>New: Added options to limit bandwidth for downloads and uploads.</li>
                    <li>New: Added progress bar to upload page.</li>
                    <li>New: Show upload (as well as download and streaming) charts in status page.</li>
                    <li>New: Added option to configure shortcuts to certain folders.</li>
                    <li>New: Rating where you can see how much each user has uploaded/downloaded/streamed.</li>
                    <li>New: Nicer layout and graphics.</li>
                    <li>New: Added option to download playlists, both current and previously saved ones.</li>
                    <li>New: Now logs to c:/subsonic/subsonic.log (Windows) or /var/subsonic/subsonic.log (other platforms).</li>
                    <li>New: Support symbolic links on Unix.</li>
                    <li>New: Support XSPF playlist format.</li>
                    <li>New: Create backup of old image file when changing cover art.</li>
                    <li>Bugfix: Avoid wrapped lines if browser window is small.</li>
                    <li>Bugfix: Use proper Y-range in bandwidth charts.</li>
                    <li>Bugfix: Integer overflow in search index creation interval.</li>
                    <li>Bugfix: Some Amazon search didn't show any results.</li>
                    <li>Bugfix: Now possible to change cover art even if original file is write protected (Windows only).</li>
                </ul>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Subsonic 2.6 - Mar 10, 2006">
                <ul>
                    <li>New: Nicer layout, colors and icons. Customizable welcome message. Option to limit number of cover art
                        images to display.</li>
                    <li>New: You can now specify multiple media folders in the configuration.
                        This is useful, for example, if you have your music on multiple disks, or if you have one directory with
                        music, and another with movies. The index (on the left-hand side) can either show all
                        media folders (merged alphabetically), or you can select from a combo box which folder to display.</li>
                    <li>New: Assign ratings (one to five stars) and comments to individual albums.</li>
                    <li>New: There is a new welcome page, displaying lists of random albums, newest albums, highest rated albums,
                        most often played albums and most recently played albums.</li>
                    <li>New: You can configure a set of links to Internet TV and radio stations. These links become available in
                        the index on the left-hand side. Click on a link, and your player connects to the station.</li>
                    <li>New: Saved playlists are now available as Podcasts (available from the "More" page).</li>
                    <li>New: Improved player management. Support multiple players with the same IP address, and players with dynamic
                        IP addresses.  Display player type (e.g., WinAmp) and last-seen date.</li>
                    <li>New: Macedonian translation by Stefan Ivanovski.</li>
                    <li>New: Implemented support for non-Latin character encodings (for instance Japanese or Cyrillic).</li>
                    <li>New: Added option to load a previously saved playlist in the WAP interface.</li>
                    <li>New: "Album Info" now integrates with Google Music.</li>
                    <li>New: Avoid unnecessary reloading of the playlist window.</li>
                    <li>Bugfix: Fallback to file name if ID3 tags are present but empty.</li>
                    <li>Bugfix: LAME now works on Linux.</li>
                    <li>Bugfix: Solved problem with playlist autoscroll on rearrange.</li>
                    <li>Bugfix: Clicking index in top frame sometimes caused reloading of left frame.</li>
                </ul>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Subsonic 2.5 - Nov 25, 2005">
                <ul>
                    <li>New: Implemented user management. Users are easily created, deleted and assigned different privileges.</li>
                    <li>New: Faster song switching. Players react immediately to playlist changes.</li>
                    <li>New: Now possible to refine search for cover art and album info.</li>
                    <li>New: Better support for OGG, AAC and other formats. Added proper suffix to stream URL as a hint to the player.</li>
                    <li>New: Display media library statistics.</li>
                    <li>New: New location for preferences, search index and database (c:\subsonic or /var/subsonic).</li>
                    <li>Bugfix: Improved parsing of MP3 tags.  Avoid funny characters in artist, album and song title.</li>
                </ul>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Subsonic 2.4 - Oct 10, 2005">
                <ul>
                    <li>New: Download cover art and album info from Amazon web service.</li>
                    <li>New: Show selection of random albums on welcome page.</li>
                    <li>New: Display notice if LAME is not installed.</li>
                    <li>Bugfix: Allow max one stream per player.</li>
                    <li>Bugfix: Use user-wide (not system-wide) preferences on non-Windows platforms.</li>
                </ul>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Subsonic 2.3 - May 28, 2005">
                <ul>
                    <li>Full internationalization support.</li>
                    <li>Automatic update of search index at specified intervals.</li>
                    <li>Search is now more like Google.</li>
                    <li>Updating search index is now a lot faster (30 seconds for 18000 songs).</li>
                    <li>Unique playlist "undo" function.</li>
                    <li>"Now Playing" automatically refreshes when a new album is played.</li>
                    <li>Ongoing downloads are now displayed in the status page, with charts showing download speed.</li>
                    <li>Some improvements in zip functionality.</li>
                    <li>Significantly improved accuracy in charts.</li>
                    <li>Better support for non-ASCII characters in SHOUTcast.</li>
                    <li>No longer necessary to enter username and password in player.</li>
                    <li>Support for "ignored articles".</li>
                    <li>Show log in help page.</li>
                </ul>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Subsonic 2.2 - March 17, 2005">
                <ul>
                    <li>Implemented SHOUTcast support.</li>
                    <li>Added "Album info" which links to reviews etc at allmusic.com.</li>
                    <li>Support for uploading files from the browser to the Subsonic server.  Zip-files are automatically unpacked.</li>
                    <li>Improved usability in search interface.</li>
                    <li>Option to specify http://yourhostname/stream/file.ogg etc.</li>
                    <li>Bugfix: Detect zero-terminated strings in ID3 tags.</li>
                    <li>Bugfix: Use ID3v2 tags instead of ID3v1, if both are present.</li>
                </ul>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Subsonic 2.1 - March 8, 2005">
                <ul>
                    <li>Added more search options.</li>
                    <li>Added support for downloading an entire directory structure as a zip file.</li>
                    <li>Subsonic now parses song titles, artists and albums from ID3 tags.</li>
                    <li>Settings for cover art size and max bitrate can now be set for individual players.</li>
                    <li>Search index is now generated in the background.</li>
                    <li>Keep position in playlist frame (e.g., always show the currently playing track).</li>
                    <li>Some minor bug fixes.</li>
                </ul>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Subsonic 2.0 - February 27, 2005">
                <ul>
                    <li>Added WAP interface for controlling Subsonic from a mobile phone or PDA.</li>
                    <li>Added option to generate a random playlist.</li>
                    <li>Added option to download and save individual songs.</li>
                    <li>Subsonic now alerts users if a new version is available.</li>
                    <li>Improved documentation and usability.</li>
                    <li>ANT support.</li>
                </ul>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Subsonic 1.0 - February 10, 2005">
                <ul>
                    <li>Added chart for displaying bitrates last few minutes.</li>
                    <li>Implemented transcoding to lower bitrates.</li>
                    <li>Added online help.</li>
                    <li>Support PLS and M3U playlists.</li>
                </ul>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Subsonic 0.1 - December 14, 2004">
                <ul>
                    <li>Initial release.</li>
                </ul>
            </subsection>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>

